# MICHELE CLAIBOURN

I am a research director – a senior data scientist, political scientist, community-engaged scholar, and senior administrator - with 20 years of experience teaching, leading, and managing research and data science teams. Recently I've been building and leading Research Data Services<sup>7</sup> in the UVA Library.

My own work has turned towards action-based research, using the tools of data science to promote accountable governance<sup>2</sup>, make visible racial and other social inequities<sup>3</sup>, and impact public policy and movement building. I am always interested in opportunities to use my experience and skills towards creating a more economically and socially just world.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Current 2015

### Director, Research Data Services & Social, Natural, and Engineering Sciences

UVA Library, University of Virginia

- · Data Science Director, Equity Center, 2020-present (partial buyout)
- · Faculty Affiliate/Lead Data Scientist, Global Policy Center, 2019-present
- · Co-Director, Community Policy, Analytics & Strategy Lab, 2018-present

2015 2013

#### Director, StatLab and Research Data Services

UVA Library, University of Virginia

· Associate Director, Data Science Institute, 2014-2016 (partial buyout)

2013 2011

#### **Data Scientist**

Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service, University of Virginia

2011 2004

### Assistant Professor

Department of Politics, University of Virginia



### **EDUCATION**

2002

### PhD., Political Science

1996

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Madison, WI

1993 1989

### **B.A.** Political Science

Rice University

OHouston, TX



### ♣■ TEACHING AND MENTORING

2020 2002

### **Graduate Courses**

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

· Public Interest Data Lab, Saving Lives with Data, Text as Data, Applied Causal Inference, General Linear Models, Linear Models, Applied Time Series, Mixed-Effects Models/Longitudinal Analysis, Introduction to Statistical Analysis

2020 2002

### **Undegraduate Courses**

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

· Project First Gen +, Research Design & Analysis, The Presidency and the Public, Media & Political Communication, Political Pscyology & Decision Making, Citizen Competence in American Democracy, Introduction to American Politics

2019 2013

### Select StatLab Workshops<sup>6</sup>

University of Virginia

· Six-part series on Data Science in R, Multiple Imputation, Cluster Analysis, Duration Models, Matching Methods, Mixed-Effects Models, Sentiment Analysis, Topic Modeling, Text Classification, Data Wrangling, Linear Modeling

### CONTACT

- mclaibourn@virginia.edu
- @ mclaibourn.github.io
- github.com/mclaibourn

linkedin.com/in/mclaibourn

See full CV and project portfolio at mclaibourn.github.io.

### Leadership

Consult with researchers and design research projects with partners seeking to better understand racial disparities and social structures, and to develop a policy response.

Founded StatLab<sup>4</sup>, a data science consulting service for members of the UVA community where I continue to serve as a senior consultant and to mentor student fellows.

Build a new division of the library enhancing our ability to support the growing data science research community at UVA, recruiting, hiring, and managing a team with diverse skills and talents to meet emerging university research needs.

Supervise a team of 10-12 fulltime staff, 3-4 graduate fellows, and research teams across mulitple collaborations on a range of research projects, including work on equity and COVID response in the Charlottesville community, racial disparities in the local child welfare systems, forced displacement events with humanitarian partners, and additional communityoriented and library-directed data science efforts.

Last updated on 2020-08-07.

Panel Chair and Moderator Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia  Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia With Paul Martin			
SELECTED PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS  Charlottesville Foster Care Study <sup>7</sup> Report to the Charlottesville Department of Social Services · With Charlotte McClintock and the Public Interest Data Lab  Panelist, Racial Equity and Technology Public Interest Technology-University Network  Panel Chair and Moderator Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia  Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin	2019		REU Mentor
<ul> <li>Charlottesville Foster Care Study<sup>7</sup> Report to the Charlottesville Department of Social Services         <ul> <li>With Charlotte McClintock and the Public Interest Data Lab</li> </ul> </li> <li>Panelist, Racial Equity and Technology         <ul> <li>Public Interest Technology-University Network</li> </ul> </li> <li>Panel Chair and Moderator         <ul> <li>Data &amp; Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia</li> </ul> </li> <li>Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses         <ul> <li>Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia</li> <li>With Paul Martin</li> </ul> </li> </ul>			School of Data Science, UVA
Report to the Charlottesville Department of Social Services  · With Charlotte McClintock and the Public Interest Data Lab  Panelist, Racial Equity and Technology Public Interest Technology-University Network  Panel Chair and Moderator Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia  Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin			SELECTED PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS
Panelist, Racial Equity and Technology Public Interest Technology-University Network  Panel Chair and Moderator Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia  Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia With Paul Martin	2019	•	Charlottesville Foster Care Study <sup>7</sup>
Panelist, Racial Equity and Technology Public Interest Technology-University Network  Panel Chair and Moderator Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia  Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin			Report to the Charlottesville Department of Social Services
Public Interest Technology-University Network  Panel Chair and Moderator Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia  Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin			· With Charlotte McClintock and the Public Interest Data Lab
Panel Chair and Moderator Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia  Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin	2020	•	Panelist, Racial Equity and Technology
Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia  Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses  Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia  · With Paul Martin			Public Interest Technology-University Network
Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia  · With Paul Martin	2019	•	Panel Chair and Moderator
Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia  · With Paul Martin			Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia
· With Paul Martin	2019	•	Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses
			Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia
			· With Paul Martin
Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters	2013	•	Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters
Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82			Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82
· With Paul Martin			· With Paul Martin
Creating Constituencies: Presidential Campaigns, Selective Mobilization, and the Scope of Conflict	2012		
Political Behavior 34: 27-56			Political Behavior 34: 27-56
· With Paul Martin			· With Paul Martin
2011 Presidential Campaigns and Presidential Accountability <sup>8</sup>	2011	•	Presidential Campaigns and Presidential Accountability $^s$
University of Illinois Press, Series on Democracy, Free Enterprise, and the Rule of Law			University of Illinois Press, Series on Democracy, Free Enterprise, and the Rule of Law
The Third Face of Social Capital: How membership in Voluntary Associations Improves Policy Accountability	2007		
Political Research Quarterly 60: 192-201			Political Research Quarterly 60: 192-201
· With Paul Martin			· With Paul Martin
Gender Differences in Citizen-Level Democratic Citizenship: Evidence from the Comparative Study of Electoral Systems	2002	•	<del>-</del>
2000	2000		Presented to the International Political Science Association (2000), the Midwest

### Teaching and Writing

20 years of experience teaching statistics and data science methods, applied policy research, and political behavior to undergraduate and graduate students.

Design data workshop series for student and adult learning communities, including recruiting and mentoring instructors, marketing and assessment, and contributing to select topics.

Experienced writer in multiple formats, from university press books and peer-reviewed journal articles, to action-oriented reports for local and state agencies, educational materials, and informal writing.

Skilled in communicating about data, technology, and policy to stakeholders, advocates, and learners.

### Methods and Software

Statistical modeling and data science R, RStudio, Shiny Data wrangling and visualization Stata and SPSS Text analytics GitHub and reproducibility Some Python and SQL Oualitative methods

## · With Paul Martin

Midwest Political Science Association Annual Meeting

Political Science Association (2001), and the Conference on Comparative Study

· 2001 Winner, Sophonisba Breckenridge Award for best paper on Women & Politics,

Trusting and Joining: An Empirical Test of the Reciprocal Nature of Social Capital

of Electoral Systems (2002)

Political Behavior 22: 267-291

· With Virginia Sapiro



2000

- 1: https://data.library.virginia.edu/
- 2: https://commpas.batten.virginia.edu/
- 3: https://virginiaequitycenter.github.io/cvilleequity\_covid/
- 4: https://data.library.virginia.edu/statlab/
- 5: https://data.library.virginia.edu/

- 6: https://data.library.virginia.edu/training/past-workshops/
- 7: https://doi.org/10.18130/v3-ztey-hn31
- 8: https://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/catalog/75hhf7en9780252035920.html